So the last section of this chapter
이 장의 마지막 절은 2.7인데요, 여기서 순열(Permutations)을 다루고,
is two point seven that talks about permutations, which
그건 지난 강의의 마지막에서 설명했죠. 그리고 전치(Transposes)도 지난 시간에 나왔어요.
There's a little more to do with those guys, permutations and transposes.
이 둘에 대해서 조금 더 다룰 게 있어요 — 순열과 전치 말이죠.
But then the heart of the lecture will be the beginning
그런데 오늘 강의의 핵심은, 어떻게 보면 선형대수학의 진짜 시작점이라고 할 수 있는 부분이에요.
of what you could say is the beginning of linear algebra, the beginning of real linear algebra which is seeing
벡터 자체를 넘어서, 벡터공간(Vector Spaces), 그리고 그 부분공간(Subspaces)을 보는 더 넓은 시야를 갖는 부분이죠.
So we're a little ahead of the syllabus, which is good, because we're coming to the place
우리는 지금 강의 진도보다 약간 앞서 있어요. 좋은 일이죠, 왜냐하면 이제부터 할 일이 많아지니까요.
where, there's a lot to do. Okay. So, to begin with permutations.
자, 그럼 순열부터 시작해봅시다.
Can I just -- so these permutations, those are matrices P and they execute
이 순열은요, P 행렬들이고, 행 교환(Row Exchanges)을 수행하는 행렬들이에요.
row exchanges.
그리고 우리는 이런 행렬들이 필요할 수 있어요. A라는 아주 좋은 행렬이 있다고 할게요 — 역행렬도 존재하고, Ax = b를 풀 수 있죠.
x=b, but to do it -- I've got to allow myself that extra freedom
그런데 그걸 풀기 위해서 — 우리는 이런 자유도가 있어야 해요.
that if a zero shows up in the pivot position I move it away.
피벗(pivot) 자리에 0이 나타나면, 그걸 다른 행과 바꿔서 0이 아닌 수로 바꿔줘야 하죠.
I get a non-zero. I get a proper pivot there by exchanging from a row below.
그래야 올바른 피벗을 갖게 되니까요.
And you've seen that already, and I just want to collect the ideas together.
여러분은 이런 과정을 이미 본 적이 있을 거예요. 지금은 이 아이디어들을 정리하고자 해요.
And principle, I could even have to do that two times, or more times.
원칙적으로는, 두 번 이상의 행 교환이 필요할 수도 있어요.
So I have to allow -- to complete the -- the theory, the possibility that I take my matrix A,
그러니까 이 이론을 완성하려면, A 행렬을 받아서 소거를 시작했는데 중간에 행을 교환해야 했고, 그걸 하고 나서 마무리했다는 가능성을 포함해야 해요.
Okay. Then all I want to do is say -- and I won't make a big project
좋아요. 제가 지금 말하고 싶은 건 — 이걸 아주 깊게 다루진 않겠지만 —
out of this -- what happens to A equal L U?
A = LU라는 식이 있을 때, 행 교환이 들어오면 어떻게 되는가예요.
So A equal L U --
A = LU는 —
this was a matrix L with ones on the diagonal and zeroes
L은 대각선에 1이 있고, 그 위는 0이고, 그 아래는 곱셈 계수들이 있는 행렬이었죠.
above and multipliers below, and this U we know, with zeroes down here.
U는 아래쪽이 0인 상삼각 행렬이고요.
That's only possible.
이건 오직 특정한 경우에만 가능한 형태예요.
That description of elimination assumes that we don't have a P, that we don't have any row exchanges.
즉, 소거 과정을 이렇게 묘사하는 건 P, 즉 행 교환이 없을 때만 해당돼요.
And now I just want to say, okay, how do I account for row exchanges? Because that doesn't.
이제 저는 "행 교환이 있을 때는 어떻게 하지?" 라는 걸 말하고 싶은 거예요.
The P in this factorization is the identity matrix.
A = LU라는 식에서, P가 항등행렬(identity matrix)이었던 경우죠.
The rows were in a good order, we left them there. Maybe I'll just add a little moment of reality,
행의 순서가 이미 좋았기 때문에 그대로 놔뒀던 거예요. 여기서 현실적인 예를 하나 덧붙이자면요,
too, about how Matlab actually does elimination.
Matlab은 소거를 할 때, 단지 피벗이 0이 아니냐만 체크하는 게 아니에요.
Matlab not only checks whether that pivot is not zero, as every human would do.
Matlab은 피벗이 충분히 "큰 수"인지도 봐요. 작은 피벗은 싫어하죠. 수치적으로 불안정하거든요.
Pivots close to zero are numerically bad. So actually if we ask Matlab to solve a system,
0에 가까운 피벗은 수치적으로 문제가 돼요. 그래서 Matlab은 Ax = b를 풀라고 하면,
it will do some elimination some row exchanges, which we don't think are necessary.
필요 없다고 생각되는 경우에도 행 교환을 몇 번 하게 돼요.
Algebra doesn't say they're necessary, but accuracy -- numerical accuracy says they are.
수학적으로는 안 해도 되지만, 수치적 정확도를 위해선 필요하죠.
Well, we're doing algebra, so here we will say, well, what do row exchanges do,
우리는 수학적인 관점에서 보고 있으니까, 정말 필요할 때만 행 교환을 하도록 해요. 하지만 필요할 수도 있어요.
And then, the result is --
그리고 그 결과가 바로 여기 숨겨져 있어요. 이게 핵심이에요.
This is the description of elimination with row exchanges. So A equal L U becomes P A equal L U.
행 교환을 포함한 소거 과정의 묘사는 이렇게 됩니다: A = LU가 아니라, PA = LU.
So this P is the matrix that does the row exchanges, and actually it does them --
여기서 P는 행을 교환해주는 행렬이에요. 실제로 행들을 올바른 순서로 정렬해줘요.
it gets the rows into the right order, into the good order where pivots will not --
즉, 피벗 자리에 0이 나타나지 않도록 해주죠. 그래서 L과 U가 위에 나왔던 것처럼 잘 나오게 돼요.
So, that's the point. Actually, I don't want to labor that point,
이게 핵심이에요. 사실 이걸 길게 설명하고 싶진 않아요.
that a permutation matrix -- and you remember what those were.
Permutation Matrix — 순열 행렬에 대해 얘기해볼게요. 여러분은 지난 시간에 배웠을 거예요.
I'll remind you from last time of what the main points about permutation matrices were --
순열 행렬의 주요 특성들을 다시 상기시키고,
and then just leave this factorization as the general case.
그리고 이 분해(PA = LU)를 일반적인 형태로 남겨둘게요.
This is -- any invertible A we get this.
모든 가역행렬 A에 대해 이게 성립해요.
For almost every one, we don't need a P. But there's that handful that do need row exchanges,
거의 대부분의 경우엔 P가 필요 없어요. 하지만 일부 경우엔 행 교환이 필요하고, 그럴 땐 이렇게 처리하는 거예요.
So permutations, P is the identity matrix
자, 마지막으로 P가 뭔지 다시 떠올려 봐요.
with reordered rows.
순열 P는, 항등행렬에서 행의 순서만 바꾼 형태예요.
I include in reordering the possibility that you just leave them the same. So the identity matrix is -- okay.
그냥 그대로 두는 경우도 포함되죠. 즉, 항등행렬도 하나의 순열이에요.
That's, like, your basic permutation matrix --
그건 가장 기본적인 순열 행렬이에요 — 아무 일도 안 하는 순열이죠.
your do-nothing permutation matrix is the identity. And then there are the ones that exchange two rows and then
그리고 두 개의 행을 바꾸는 행렬, 세 개, 네 개의 행을 바꾸는 행렬도 있어요.
well, it gets a little -- it gets more interesting algebraically
만약 4개의 행이 있다면, 그걸 한 바퀴 돌리는 순환 순열도 있을 수 있어요. 1→2, 2→3, 3→4, 4→1처럼요.
Or you might have -- exchange one and two and three and four.
혹은 1과 2, 3과 4를 각각 바꾸는 식도 있겠죠.
Lots of possibilities there. In fact, how many possibilities?
굉장히 다양한 경우의 수가 생겨요. 그럼 그 수는 얼마나 될까요?
The answer was (n)factorial. This is n(n-1)(n-2)...
정답은 팩토리얼(factorial)이에요. n × (n-1) × (n-2) × ... × 1.
(3)(2)(1). That's the number of -- this counts the reorderings,
이건 가능한 재배열의 수를 의미해요.
the possible reorderings. So it counts all the n by n permutations.
즉, n × n 순열 행렬의 개수예요.
because we can bring those rows back into the normal order.
행을 다시 제자리로 돌리는 행렬이 있으니까요. 그게 바로 P의 전치(transpose)예요.
You might take a permutation matrix, multiply by its transpose and you will see how --
P에 전치를 곱해보면, 1들이 서로 맞아 떨어져서 항등행렬이 나오게 돼요.
matrix. So this is a -- we'll be highly interested in matrices
우리는 이런 성질이 좋은 행렬들에 관심이 많을 거예요.
that have nice properties. And one property that -- maybe I could rewrite that as P
이를 다른 말로 표현하면, Pᵀ × P = I 라는 식이죠.
transpose P is the identity. That tells me in other words that this
이건 곧, 전치가 역행렬이라는 걸 의미해요.
P equal the identity. There are more of them than just permutations, but my point right now is that permutations are like a little
우리는 이런 행렬에 관심이 있어요. 단지 순열뿐만 아니라, 다른 경우도 포함되지만 지금 중요한 건, 순열 행렬이 그런 특수 행렬들의 중심에 있다는 거예요.
Okay. So now we know how many there are.
자, 이제 우리는 그 개수도 알아요.
Twenty four in the case of -- there are twenty four four by four permutations, there are five factorial which is
4×4 순열은 총 24개였죠. 5!은 120이니까, 5×24 = 120이 되겠네요. 5×5 순열을 전부 나열하는 건 별로 재미 없을 거예요.
Okay. So that's permutations.
좋아요, 여기까지가 순열이에요.
Now also in section two seven is some discussion of transposes.
그리고 이제 2.7절에는 전치(transpose)에 대한 설명도 들어 있어요.
And can I just complete that discussion. First of all, I haven't even transposed a matrix
그걸 이제 마무리해볼게요. 우선, 아직 칠판에 전치된 행렬을 안 써봤네요?
on the board here, have I? So I'd better do it. So suppose I take a matrix like (1 2 4; 3 3 1).
한 번 써봐야겠어요. 예를 들어 (1 2 4; 3 3 1) 같은 행렬이 있다고 해봅시다.
It's a rectangular matrix, three by two.
직사각형 행렬이죠. 3행 2열이에요.
And I want to transpose it. So what's --
이걸 전치하면 어떻게 될까요?
I'll use a T, also Matlab would use a prime.
전치 기호로 T를 쓰겠습니다. Matlab에서는 ' (프라임)을 써요.
And the result will be -- I'll right it here, because this was three rows and two columns,
결과는 — 여기 써볼게요. 원래는 3행 2열이었는데,
this was a three by two matrix. The transpose will be two rows and three columns,
전치하면 2행 3열이 되죠.
two by three. So it's short and wider.
즉, 더 짧고 더 넓어진 형태예요.
And, of course, that row -- that column becomes a row --
물론, 열(column)은 행(row)이 되고 —
that column becomes the other row. And at the same time, that row became a column.
각 열이 행으로 바뀌어요. 동시에, 행도 열로 바뀌어요.
This row became a column. Oh, what's the general formula for the transpose?
이 행도 열이 된 거죠. 자, 그럼 일반적인 전치 공식은 뭘까요?
So the transpose --
전치는 —
you see it in numbers. What I'm going to write is the same thing in symbols.
지금 숫자로 본 걸 기호로 표현하면 똑같은 거예요.
The numbers are the clearest, of course. But in symbols, if I take A transpose
물론 숫자로 보는 게 가장 직관적이지만, 기호로도 써볼게요.
and I ask what number is in row I and column J of A transpose?
A의 전치에서, i행 j열의 값은 뭐가 될까요?
Well, it came out of A.
그 값은 A에서 나온 거예요.
It came out A by this flip across the main diagonal.
주대각선(main diagonal)을 기준으로 뒤집어서 나온 거죠.
And, actually, it was the number in A
그리고 실제로, 그건 A의 원소 중 J행 I열에 있던 값이에요.
which was in row J, column I.
그래서 행과 열의 인덱스가 서로 바뀐다는 거예요.
So the row and column -- the row and column numbers just get reversed.
행 번호가 열 번호가 되고, 열 번호가 행 번호가 되는 거죠. 문제없어요.
Okay. Now, a special -- the best matrices, we could say.
좋아요. 이제 특별한 — 가장 좋은 행렬들을 볼게요.
In a lot of applications, symmetric matrices show up.
많은 응용 분야에서, 대칭 행렬(symmetric matrix)이 나타나요.
So can I just call attention to symmetric matrices?
그래서 대칭 행렬에 주목해 볼게요.
What does that mean? What does that word symmetric mean? It means that this transposing doesn't change the matrix.
'symmetric'라는 말은 무슨 뜻일까요? 이 말은, 전치(transpose)해도 행렬이 바뀌지 않는다는 뜻이에요.
A transpose equals A. And an example.
A의 전치가 A와 같다는 거죠.
So, let's take a matrix that's symmetric,
예제를 하나 들어보죠. 대칭인 행렬을 생각해 볼게요.
so whatever is sitting on the diagonal -- but now what's above the diagonal, like a one,
대각선 위에 어떤 값이든 괜찮아요 — 하지만 대각선 위쪽에 있는 값이, 아래쪽에도 있어야 해요. 예를 들어 1이 위에 있으면, 그 아래도 1, 7이 있으면 아래도 7, 9도 마찬가지죠.
There's a symmetric matrix. I happened to use all positive numbers as its entries.
이런 게 대칭 행렬이에요. 전 숫자를 모두 양수로 썼지만,
That's not the point. The point is that if I transpose that matrix, I get it back again.
그게 핵심은 아니에요. 핵심은, 전치를 해도 똑같은 행렬이 다시 나온다는 거예요.
So symmetric matrices have this property A transpose equals A. I guess at this point --
즉, Aᵀ = A. 이게 대칭 행렬의 특징이에요. 여기서 제가 말씀드리고 싶은 건,
I'm just asking you to notice this family of matrices that
전치해도 바뀌지 않는 행렬들의 집합이 있다는 거예요.
are unchanged by transposing. And they're easy to identify, of course.
그리고 이건 쉽게 알아볼 수 있어요.
You know, it's not maybe so easy before we had a case where
예전엔 전치가 역행렬이 되는 경우도 봤죠. 그건 중요하지만, 이해하기 쉬운 건 아니에요.
This is the case where the transpose gives the same matrix back again. That's totally simple to see.
지금의 경우처럼, 전치해도 그대로 나오는 경우는 확실히 쉽게 볼 수 있어요.
Okay. Could actually -- maybe I could even say when would we get such
좋아요. 그럼 이런 행렬이 어떻게 생길 수 있는지 볼까요?
a matrix? For example, this -- that matrix is absolutely far from
예를 들어, 아까 본 저 행렬은 절대 대칭이 아니었죠.
symmetric, right? The transpose isn't even the same shape --
전치해도 모양 자체가 다르잖아요 — 직사각형이니까, 전치하면 눕게 되죠.
But let me tell you a way to get a symmetric matrix out of this.
하지만 이걸 대칭 행렬로 바꿀 수 있는 방법이 있어요.
Multiply those together. If I multiply this rectangular, shall I
곱해보세요. 이 직사각형 행렬 — 이름을 R이라고 할게요. (rectangular)
call it R for rectangular? So let that be R for rectangular matrix
그럼 Rᵀ은 그 전치(transpose)겠죠. 이 둘을 곱하면,
and let that be R transpose, which it is. Then I think that if I multiply those together,
대칭 행렬이 나올 거예요.
I get a symmetric matrix. Can I just do it with the numbers and then ask you why, how did I know it would be symmetric?
이걸 숫자로 계산해보면 대칭이 되는 걸 볼 수 있고, 왜 그런지도 생각해볼 수 있어요.
So my point is that R transpose R is always symmetric.
중요한 건, RᵀR은 항상 대칭이라는 거예요.
Okay?
좋아요?
And I'm going to do it for that particular R transpose R which was --
지금 계산해보려는 건 지금 우리가 만든 이 RᵀR이에요.
let's see, the column was one two four three three one.
Rᵀ의 열은 1 2 4, 그리고 3 3 1 이었죠.
I called that one R transpose, didn't I, and I called this guy one two four three three one.
제가 그걸 Rᵀ이라 불렀고, 다른 건 R이라고 했어요. 맞죠?
I called that R. Shall we just do that multiplication? Okay, so up here I'm getting a ten.
그럼 계산해봅시다. 위쪽 원소는 10이 나와요.
Next to it I'm getting two, a nine, I'm getting an eleven. Next to that I'm getting four and three, a seven.
그 옆은 2, 9, 다음은 11, 그 다음은 4, 3, 7이 나와요.
Now what do I get there? This eleven came from one three times two three, right?
그 11은 1×3 + 3×3에서 나온 거죠? 1행 2열에서요.
Row one, column two. What goes here? Row two, column one.
그럼 반대쪽은요? 2행 1열에서 나온 값은?
But no difference. One three two three or two three one three, same thing.
결과는 똑같죠. 1×3 + 3×3이니까요. 순서만 바뀐 거예요.
It's going to be an eleven. That's the symmetry. I can continue to fill it out.
결과는 11이에요. 이게 바로 대칭성(symmetric)의 핵심이죠.
What -- oh, let's get that seven. That seven will show up down here, too, and then four more numbers.
이제 나머지도 채워볼 수 있어요.
That seven will show up here because one three times four one gave the seven, but also four one times one three
그 7도 아래쪽에 반복되죠. 그 외에 4개의 숫자만 더 있으면 돼요.
will give that seven. Do you see that it works?
1×4 + 3×1에서 나온 7은 4×1 + 1×3으로도 다시 나오죠.
Actually, do you want to see it work also in matrix language?
이게 잘 작동하는 걸 알 수 있죠?
I mean, that's quite convincing, right? That seven is no accident.
이걸 기호로도 볼 수 있어요. 행렬 언어로 표현하면요.
The eleven is no accident.
그 7은 우연히 나온 게 아니에요.
But just tell me how do I know if I transpose this guy --
11도 마찬가지예요.
How do I know it's symmetric? Well, I'm going to transpose it. And when I transpose it, I'm hoping
그럼 이걸 전치했을 때 대칭인지 어떻게 알 수 있을까요?
I get the matrix back again. So can I transpose R transpose R?
전치해봤을 때, 그 결과가 원래 행렬과 같다면 대칭이죠.
So just -- so, why?
그럼 RᵀR을 전치해보죠.
Well, my suggestion is take the transpose.
왜 그런 결과가 나오는지를 볼 수 있어요.
That's the only way to show it's symmetric. Take the transpose and see that it didn't change. Okay, so I take the transpose of R transpose R.
이게 대칭임을 보이는 유일한 방법은 전치를 해보고 바뀌었는지를 확인하는 거예요.
Okay. How do I do that? This is our little practice on the rules for transposes.
좋아요, 그럼 RᵀR의 전치를 해봅시다.
So the rule for transposes is the order gets reversed.
이건 전치 규칙(transpose rule) 연습이에요.
Just like inverses, which we did prove, same rule for transposes and -- which we'll now use.
규칙은, 곱의 전치는 순서를 바꿔서 각각 전치하는 거예요.
So the order gets reversed. It's the transpose of that that comes first,
즉, 전치된 순서로 두 행렬이 나와요.
and the transpose of this that comes -- no.
첫 번째는 뒤쪽 행렬을 전치한 것이고,
Is that -- yeah. That's what I have to write, right? This is a product of two matrices and I want its
두 번째는 앞쪽 행렬을 전치한 것이죠.
transpose. So I put the matrices in the opposite order and I transpose them. But what have I got here?
그럼 여기서 Rᵀᵀ은 뭘까요?
Well, don't all speak at once. R transpose transpose, I flipped over the diagonal,
다 같이 말하지는 마세요. Rᵀᵀ은 한 번 뒤집고, 또 한 번 뒤집은 거죠.
I flipped over the diagonal again, so I've got R.
결국 원래대로 돌아오니까 R이죠.
And that's just my point, that if I started with this matrix, I transposed it, I got it back again.
이게 핵심이에요. 시작한 행렬을 전치하고 또 전치하면 원래 행렬이 나오는 거예요.
So that's the check, without using numbers, but with --
그래서 숫자 없이도 확인이 되죠.
it checked in two lines that I always get symmetric matrices
두 줄짜리 계산으로 항상 대칭 행렬이 나온다는 걸 보여줬어요.
this way. And actually, that's where they come from in so many practical applications.
그리고 실제로 많은 응용에서 이런 방식으로 대칭 행렬이 생겨나요.
Okay. So now I've said something today about permutations and about
좋아요. 오늘 저는 순열(Permutation), 전치(Transpose), 대칭성(Symmetry)에 대해 설명했고,
transposes and about symmetry and I'm ready
이제 3장을 시작할 준비가 됐어요. 잠깐 숨 돌릴까요 —
the tape won't take a breath, but the lecturer will, because to tell you about vector spaces is --
녹화 테이프는 쉬지 않지만 강사는 좀 쉬어야겠네요. 왜냐하면 이제 벡터공간(Vector Spaces)을 설명해야 하니까요.
we really have to start now and think, okay, listen up.
자, 이제 집중해 주세요.
What are vector spaces?
벡터공간이란 무엇인가요?
And what are sub-spaces? Okay. So, the point is, The main operations that we do --
그리고 부분공간(Subspaces)은 뭘까요? 우리가 주로 하는 연산은 뭐죠?
what do we do with vectors? We add them. We know how to add two vectors.
벡터로 뭘 하죠? 더해요. 벡터끼리 더하는 걸 알고 있죠.
We multiply them by numbers, usually called scalers.
또 숫자를 곱해요. 보통 스칼라(Scalar)라고 하죠.
If we have a vector, we know what three V is. If we have a vector V and W, we know what V plus W is.
벡터 V가 있으면, 3V가 뭔지 알고 있어요. 벡터 V와 W가 있으면, V + W가 뭔지도 알아요.
Those are the two operations that we've got to be able to do.
이 두 가지 연산이 기본이에요.
To legitimately talk about a space of vectors, the requirement is that we should
어떤 집합이 벡터공간이라고 말하려면 이 연산들을 할 수 있어야 해요.
be able to add the things and multiply by numbers and that there should be some decent rules satisfied.
즉, 덧셈과 스칼라 곱이 가능해야 하고, 어떤 기본적인 규칙들을 만족해야 해요.
Okay. So let me start with examples. So I'm talking now about vector spaces.
좋아요. 그럼 예시부터 시작해 볼게요. 이제 벡터공간에 대해 이야기합니다.
Let me say again what this word space is meaning. When I say that word space, that means to me
먼저, '공간(space)'이라는 말이 무슨 뜻인지 다시 말할게요. '공간'이란 말은 저에게
that I've got a bunch of vectors, a space of vectors.
벡터들이 모인 어떤 집합을 의미해요 — 그냥 아무 벡터 집합이 아니라,
But not just any bunch of vectors. It has to be a space of vectors --
벡터공간이라는 말은 벡터에 적합한 연산이 가능한 공간이어야 해요.
has to allow me to do the operations that vectors are for. I have to be able to add vectors and multiply by numbers.
벡터끼리 더할 수 있어야 하고, 숫자를 곱할 수 있어야 하죠.
I have to be able to take linear combinations. Well, where did we meet linear combinations?
선형 결합(linear combination)을 만들 수 있어야 해요. 그런 건 어디서 봤죠?
We met them back in, say in R^2.
우리는 R²에서 그런 걸 봤어요.
So there's a vector space. What's that vector space?
그럼 그게 어떤 벡터공간인지 봅시다.
So R two is telling me I'm talking about real numbers
R²는 실수(real number) 두 개를 의미해요.
and I'm talking about two real numbers. So this is all two dimensional vectors --
즉, 두 실수로 이루어진 벡터들이라는 뜻이에요.
real, such as --
예를 들어 이런 벡터들 — |3; 2|, |0; 0|, |π; e| 등등이죠.
So on.
이런 식으로요.
And it's natural -- okay. Let's see, I guess I should do algebra first.
그리고 이건 아주 자연스러운 거예요. 이제 대수부터 봅시다.
Algebra means what can I do to these vectors? I can add them. I can add that to that.
대수라는 건, 이런 벡터들에 무슨 연산을 할 수 있느냐예요. 더할 수 있어요.
And how do I do it? A component at a time, of course. Three two added to zero zero gives me, three two.
이 벡터와 저 벡터를 더할 수 있어요.
Sorry about that. Three two added to pi e gives me three plus pi, two plus e.
어떻게 더하죠? 각 성분별로 더하죠. (3,2) + (0,0)은 (3,2).
Oh, you know what it does. And you know the picture that goes with it.
아, 이게 뭘 하는지 아시죠. 그리고 이 벡터에 대한 그림도 떠오를 거예요.
There's the vector three two. And often, the picture has an arrow.
여기 벡터 (3,2)가 있어요. 그림에는 보통 화살표가 그려지죠.
The vector zero zero, which is a highly important vector -- it's got, like, the most important here
그리고 벡터 (0,0)는 굉장히 중요한 벡터예요 — 아마 가장 중요한 벡터일 거예요.
-- is there. And of course there's not much of an arrow.
그 자리에 있어야 하고, 당연히 화살표는 거의 없겠죠.
Pi -- I'll have to remember -- pi is about three and a little
π는... 기억해야겠네요 — π는 대략 3보다 약간 크고,
more, e is about two and a little more. So maybe there's pi e.
e는 대략 2보다 약간 크죠. 그러니까 아마 (π,e)는 이쯤일 거예요.
I never drew pi e before. It's just natural to --
π와 e 벡터는 제가 그려본 적 없네요. 하지만 아주 자연스러워요.
this is the first component on the horizontal
첫 번째 성분은 수평 방향이고,
and this is the second component, going up the vertical.
두 번째 성분은 수직으로 올라가는 방향이에요.
Okay. And the whole plane is R two.
좋아요. 전체 평면이 R²입니다.
So R two is, we could say, the plane.
그러니까 R²는, 말하자면, 평면이에요.
The xy plane. That's what everybody thinks.
xy 평면이죠. 다들 그렇게 생각하죠.
But the point is it's a vector space because all those vectors
하지만 핵심은, 이건 벡터공간이라는 거예요. 왜냐하면 모든 벡터들이 그 안에 들어 있으니까요.
are in there. If I removed one of them -- Suppose I removed zero zero.
그 중 하나를 빼버리면 — 예를 들어 (0,0)을 뺀다고 해봅시다.
Suppose I tried to take the -- considered the X Y plane with a puncture, with a point removed.
xy 평면에서 점 하나를 뺀, 구멍 난 평면을 생각해 보세요.
Like the origin. That would be, like, awful to take the origin away. Why is that?
즉, 원점을 뺀다면요. 그건 끔찍한 일이에요. 왜일까요?
Why do I need the origin there? Because I have to be allowed -- if I had these other vectors,
왜 원점이 꼭 있어야 할까요? 왜냐하면 다른 벡터들이 있다면,
I have to be allowed to multiply three two -- this was three two --
예를 들어 이 (3,2) 벡터가 있다면 — 이걸 어떤 수로든 곱할 수 있어야 하니까요. 0도 포함해서요.
by anything, by any scaler, including zero. I've got to be allowed to multiply by zero
0으로 곱하는 것도 가능해야 하고, 결과 벡터도 그 공간 안에 있어야 해요.
and the result's got to be there. I can't do without that point.
그 점이 없으면 안 돼요.
And I have to be able to add three two to the opposite guy,
그리고 (3,2)와 그 반대인 (-3,-2)를 더했을 때,
minus three minus two. And if I add those I'm back to the origin again.
다시 원점으로 돌아가야 해요.
No way I can do without the origin. Every vector space has got that zero vector in it.
원점 없이 벡터공간은 성립하지 않아요. 모든 벡터공간에는 0 벡터가 있어야 해요.
Okay, that's an easy vector space, because we have a natural picture of it.
좋아요, 이건 쉬운 예제예요. 그림으로 쉽게 이해할 수 있는 벡터공간이죠.
Okay. Similarly easy is R^3.
R³도 마찬가지로 쉽습니다.
This would be all -- let me go up a little here. This would be --
위로 좀 올라가볼게요. 이건 — R³는 3차원 벡터 전체를 말해요. 또는 세 개의 실수 성분을 가진 벡터들이죠.
Okay.
좋아요.
Let me just to be sure we're together,
우리가 같은 얘기를 하고 있는지 확실히 하려고,
let me take the vector three two zero.
(3,2,0) 벡터를 한번 봅시다.
Is that a vector in R^2 or R^3? Definitely it's in R^3.
이건 R²에 속하나요, R³에 속하나요? 명백하게 R³에 속하죠.
It's got three components. One of them happens to be zero, but that's a perfectly okay number.
성분이 3개예요. 하나가 0이긴 해도 괜찮아요. 0도 실수니까요.
So that's a vector in R^3. We don't want to mix up the --
그래서 이건 R³에 속하는 벡터예요. 혼동하면 안 돼요.
I mean, keep these vectors straight and keep R^n straight. So what's R^n?
벡터를 정확히 구분해야 하고, Rⁿ도 정확히 알아야 해요. 그럼 Rⁿ은 뭘까요?
R^n. So this is our big example, is all vectors with n components.
Rⁿ — 이건 아주 중요한 예제예요. 성분이 n개인 모든 벡터들을 말해요.
And I'm making these darn things column vectors.
그리고 전부 열 벡터(column vector)로 쓰고 있어요.
Can I try to follow that convention, that they'll be column vectors, and their components should
그 규칙을 따르겠습니다. 열 벡터로 쓰고, 성분들은 실수입니다.
be real numbers. Later we'll need complex numbers and complex vectors,
나중엔 복소수와 복소 벡터도 다루겠지만, 그건 훨씬 나중 일이에요.
but much later. Okay. So that's a vector space.
좋아요. 이건 벡터공간이에요.
Now, let's see. What do I have to tell you about vector spaces? I said the most important thing, which is that we can add any
이제 벡터공간에 대해 뭘 말씀드려야 할까요? 제가 가장 중요한 말은 했어요 — R²의 어떤 두 벡터를 더해도 여전히 R²에 있고,
two of these and we -- still in R^2. We can multiply by any number and we're still in R^2.
어떤 수를 곱해도 여전히 R²에 있어요.
We can take any combination and we're still in R^2. And same goes for R^n.
어떤 조합을 만들어도 R²에 있어요. Rⁿ도 마찬가지예요.
It's -- honesty requires me to mention that these operations
그리고 이제 솔직히 말씀드려야겠죠. 이러한 덧셈과 곱셈 연산은
of adding and multiplying have to obey a few rules.
몇 가지 규칙을 따라야 해요.
Like, we can't just arbitrarily say, okay, the sum of three two and pi e is zero zero.
예를 들어, 우리가 임의로 (3,2) + (π,e) = (0,0)이라고 하면 안 돼요.
It's not. The sum of three two and minus three two is zero zero.
그건 아니에요. (3,2) + (-3,-2)가 (0,0)인 건 맞지만요.
So -- oh, I'm not going to -- the book, actually, lists the eight rules that the addition and multiplication
사실 책에는 덧셈과 곱셈이 따라야 할 8가지 규칙이 나와 있어요.
have to satisfy, but they do. They certainly satisfy it in R^n and usually it's not those
하지만 Rⁿ에서는 그 규칙들을 다 만족해요. 보통 문제는 그 8가지 규칙이 아니에요.
eight rules that are in doubt. What's -- the question is, can we do those additions and do we
문제는, 덧셈이나 곱셈을 했을 때 그 공간 안에 여전히 있는지예요.
stay in the space? Let me show you a case where you can't.
그게 안 되는 예를 하나 보여드릴게요.
So suppose this is going to be not a vector space.
그래서 이건 벡터공간이 아닌 경우가 됩니다.
Suppose I take the xy plane -- so there's R^2. That is a vector space.
xy 평면, 즉 R²는 벡터공간이에요.
Now suppose I just take part of it. Just this.
그런데 이제 그 일부만 가져올게요. 예를 들어 이 부분만요.
Just this one -- this is one quarter of the vector space.
벡터 성분이 둘 다 0 이상인 1사분면 부분만 취한다고 해봅시다.
All the vectors with positive or at least not negative
그럼 이런 경우엔 덧셈은 안전할까요?
Yes. If I add a vector with, like, two -- three two to another vector like five six,
예, 덧셈은 괜찮아요. (3,2)와 (5,6)을 더하면 여전히 1사분면에 있어요.
I'm still up in this quarter, no problem with adding. But there's a heck of a problem with multiplying by scalers,
덧셈은 문제없어요. 하지만 스칼라 곱에서는 큰 문제가 생깁니다.
because there's a lot of scalers that will take me out of this quarter plane, like negative ones.
왜냐하면 음수를 곱하면 그 공간을 벗어나기 때문이죠.
If I took three two and I multiplied by minus five, I'm way down here.
(3,2)에 -5를 곱하면 저 아래쪽 어딘가로 가버려요.
So that's not a vector space, because it's not -- closed is the right word.
그래서 이건 벡터공간이 아니에요. 왜냐하면 닫힘(closed) 조건을 만족하지 않기 때문이죠.
It's not closed under multiplication by all real numbers.
실수 전체에 대해 곱셈이 닫혀 있지 않아요.
So a vector space has to be closed under multiplication
즉, 벡터공간은 벡터의 덧셈과 곱셈에 대해 닫혀 있어야 해요.
and addition of vectors. In other words, linear combinations. It -- so, it means that if I give you a few vectors --
다시 말해, 선형결합(linear combination)이 가능해야 해요. 그러니까, 몇 개의 벡터를 주면 —
yeah look, here's an important -- here -- now we're getting to some really important vector spaces. Well, R^n -- like, they are the most important.
이제 정말 중요한 예로 갑니다. Rⁿ이야말로 가장 중요한 벡터공간이죠.
But we will be interested in so- in vector spaces that are
그런데 우리는 Rⁿ 내부의 부분 벡터공간에도 관심을 가져요.
inside R^n. Vector spaces that follow the rules, but they --
규칙은 따르지만, Rⁿ 전체가 아니라 그 안의 일부인 거죠.
we don't need all of -- see, there we started with R^2 here,
아까 R²에서 시작해서,
and took part of it and messed it up. What we got was not a vector space.
그 중 일부만 가져왔더니 벡터공간이 아니게 됐어요.
Now tell me a vector space that is part of R^2 and is still
그럼 이번엔 R²의 일부면서도 진짜 벡터공간인 경우를 보여드릴게요.
safely -- we can multiply, we can add and we stay in this
그 공간 안에서 덧셈과 곱셈을 해도 여전히 그 공간 안에 머무는 경우요.
smaller vector space. So it's going to be called a subspace. So I'm going to change this bad example to a good one.
그걸 우리는 부분공간(subspace)이라고 부릅니다. 앞서 말한 나쁜 예제를 이제 좋은 예제로 바꿔볼게요.
Okay. So I'm going to start again with R^2, but I'm going to take an example -- it is a vector space,
R²에서 다시 시작해서, 이번에는 진짜 벡터공간인 예제를 봅시다.
so it'll be a vector space inside R^2.
그러면 이건 R² 내부의 벡터공간이 될 거예요.
And we'll call that a subspace of R^2.
그래서 우리는 그걸 R²의 부분공간이라고 부릅니다.
Okay. What can I do?
좋아요. 뭘 할 수 있을까요?
It's got something in it. Suppose it's got this vector in it.
무언가 벡터 하나는 들어 있어야 해요. 예를 들어 이 벡터가 있다고 해봅시다.
Okay. If that vector's in my little subspace
이 벡터가 내 부분공간에 포함돼 있다면,
and it's a true subspace, then there's got to be some more in it,
진짜 부분공간이라면 그와 관련된 다른 벡터들도 있어야 하겠죠?
right? I have to be able to multiply that by two, and that double vector has to be included.
예를 들어 그걸 2배한 벡터도 있어야 하고,
Have to be able to multiply by zero, that vector, or by half, or by three quarters.
0배, 1/2배, 3/4배도 있어야 해요.
All these vectors. Or by minus a half, or by minus one.
-1/2배, -1배도 있어야 해요.
I have to be able to multiply by any number. So that is going to say that I have to have that whole line.
모든 실수에 대해 곱해진 벡터가 있어야 해요. 즉, 그 벡터가 포함되어 있다면 그 벡터가 놓인 직선 전체가 있어야 해요.
Do you see that? Once I get a vector in there --
무슨 말인지 아시겠죠? 벡터 하나가 있으면
I've got the whole line of all multiples of that vector. I can't have a vector space without extending to get
그걸 포함하는 직선 전체가 있어야 해요. 그 선형 결합까지 포함되지 않으면 벡터공간이 안 돼요.
those multiples in there. Now I still have to check addition.
이제 덧셈 조건도 확인해야겠죠.
But that comes out okay. This line is going to work, because I could add something
하지만 이 직선이라면 괜찮아요. 직선 위의 벡터끼리 더하면 여전히 직선 위에 있어요.
So, example. So this is all examples of a subspace --
예제입니다. 이건 부분공간의 예제예요 — 우리 예제는 R² 안의 직선이에요. 단, 아무 직선이 아니에요.
If I took this line, would that --
이런 직선을 생각해보죠. 이 직선 위의 모든 벡터들 — 예: 이 벡터, 저 벡터, 또 다른 벡터들.
-- in lighter type, I'm drawing something that doesn't work.
제가 지금 연하게 그리고 있는 건 부분공간이 아닌 예제예요.
It's not a subspace. The line in R^2 -- to be a subspace, the line in R^2 must go through the zero vector.
왜냐하면 R² 안에서 부분공간이 되려면 그 직선은 반드시 원점을 지나야 해요.
Because -- why is this line no good?
왜 이 직선은 안 될까요?
Let me do a dashed line.
점선(dashed line)으로 표시해볼게요.
Because if I multiplied that vector on the dashed line by zero, then I'm down here, I'm not on the dashed line.
이 점선 위의 어떤 벡터에 0을 곱하면, 이 아래로 내려오게 돼요. 점선 위에 있지 않게 되죠.
Z- zero's got to be. Every subspace has got to contain zero --
그러니까 0 벡터는 반드시 있어야 해요. 모든 부분공간에는 0 벡터가 반드시 있어야 해요.
because I must be allowed to multiply by zero and that will always give me the zero vector.
왜냐하면 어떤 벡터든 0을 곱했을 때 항상 0 벡터가 되기 때문이죠.
Okay. Now, I was going to make --
좋아요. 이제 부분공간을 몇 개 만들어 보려 해요.
create some subspaces. Oh, while I'm in R^2, why don't we think of all
R² 안에 있는 동안, 가능한 모든 경우를 한번 생각해보죠.
the possibilities. R two, there can't be that many. So what are the possible subspaces of R^2?
R²에서는 경우가 그리 많지 않아요. 그럼 가능한 부분공간들은 뭐가 있을까요?
Let me list them. So I'm listing now the subspaces of R^2.
지금부터 R²의 부분공간들을 나열해볼게요.
And one possibility that we always allow
첫 번째로 항상 가능한 경우는 —
is all of R two, the whole thing, the whole space.
R² 전체, 전체 공간입니다.
That counts as a subspace of itself. You always want to allow that.
전체 공간도 자기 자신에 대한 부분공간으로 인정돼요. 항상 포함시켜야 해요.
Then the others are lines -- any line, meaning infinitely far in both directions
그리고 나머지들은 직선입니다 — 무한히 양쪽으로 뻗은 직선, 단, 원점을 지나야 해요.
through the zero.
그건 마치 전체 공간과도 비슷하고 — 이건 2차원 전체 공간이죠.
This is like one dimension. Is this line the same as R^1 ? No.
이건 일차원이라고 볼 수 있어요. 이 직선이 R¹과 같을까요? 아니요.
You could say it looks a lot like R^1. R^1 was just a line and this is a line.
겉보기엔 R¹과 매우 비슷해요. R¹도 직선이고, 이것도 직선이니까요.
But this is a line inside R^2. The vectors here have two components.
하지만 이건 R² 안의 직선이에요. 벡터들이 성분 두 개를 가지고 있어요.
So that's not the same as R^1, because there the vectors only have one component.
그래서 R¹과는 달라요. R¹에서는 벡터가 성분 하나만 가집니다.
Very close, you could say, but not the same. Okay. And now there's a third possibility.
아주 비슷하긴 하지만, 같지는 않아요. 좋아요, 이제 세 번째 경우가 있어요.
There's a third subspace that's --
R²의 세 번째 부분공간은 —
of R^2 that's not the whole thing, and it's not a line.
전체 공간도 아니고, 직선도 아니에요.
It's even less. It's just the zero vector alone. The zero vector alone, only.
더 작은 거예요. 바로 0 벡터 하나만 있는 경우예요.
I'll often call this subspace Z, just for zero. Here's a line, L.
전 이 부분공간을 Z라고 부르기도 해요. Zero에서 따온 이름이죠. 직선은 L, 전체 평면은 R²라고 부를게요.
Here's a plane, all of R^2. So, do you see that the zero vector's okay?
자, 이제 0 벡터 하나만 있는 것도 괜찮은가를 봐야 해요.
You would just -- to understand subspaces, we have to know the rules -- and knowing the rules means that we
부분공간의 의미를 이해하려면 규칙을 알아야 하고 — 규칙을 안다는 건 곧 이런 것도 확인해야 해요.
have to see that yes, the zero vector by itself, just this guy alone satisfies the rules.
0 벡터 하나만 있는 경우도 규칙을 만족하는가?
Why's that? Oh, it's too dumb to tell you. If I took that and added it to itself, I'm still there.
왜 그럴까요? 너무 당연해서 설명하기가 민망할 정도예요. 이걸 자기 자신과 더하면 그대로예요.
If I took that and multiplied by seventeen, I'm still there. So I've done the operations, adding and multiplying
17을 곱해도 여전히 그대로예요. 즉, 필요한 연산 — 덧셈, 스칼라 곱을 해도 여전히 그 공간 안에 있어요.
by numbers, that are required, and I didn't go outside this one point space.
어떤 연산을 해도 이 한 점을 벗어나지 않아요.
So that's always -- that's the littlest subspace.
그래서 이건 항상 유효한 가장 작은 부분공간이에요.
And the largest subspace is the whole thing and in-between come all --
가장 큰 부분공간은 전체 공간이고, 그 사이엔 —
whatever's in between. Okay. So for example, what's in between for R^3?
뭐든지 중간에 올 수 있겠죠.
So if I'm in ordinary three dimensions, the subspace is R, all of R^3 at one extreme, the zero vector at the bottom.
예를 들어, R³에서는 어떤 경우가 있을까요?
And then a plane, a plane through the origin.
3차원 공간에서는 한쪽 끝이 전체 공간 R³이고, 다른 쪽 끝은 0 벡터 하나예요.
Or a line, a line through the origin. So with R^3, the subspaces were R^3, plane through the origin,
그 중간은? 원점을 지나는 평면이 하나 있고,
line through the origin and a zero vector by itself, zero zero zero, just that single vector.
또 원점을 지나는 직선도 있어요. 결국 R³에서는 네 가지가 가능한 거예요: 전체 공간, 평면, 직선, 그리고 0 벡터 하나.
Okay, you've got the idea. But, now comes --
좋아요. 이제 개념은 잡히셨죠. 이제 진짜 중요한 질문은 —
the reality is -- what are these -- where do these subspaces come --
실제로 이런 부분공간들이 어디서 오는가? 행렬과 어떻게 연결되는가?
how do they come out of matrices? And I want to take this matrix --
그걸 이야기하려고 해요. 자, 이 행렬을 가져와 봅시다.
oh, let me take that matrix. So I want to create some subspaces out of that matrix.
그 행렬로부터 부분공간을 만들어보려고 해요.
Well, one subspace is from the columns.
그 중 하나는 열(column)들로부터 나오는 부분공간이에요.
Okay. So this is the important subspace,
이게 바로 중요한 부분공간입니다.
the first important subspace that comes from that matrix -- I'm going to -- let me call it A again.
행렬로부터 나오는 첫 번째 중요한 부분공간이죠 — 이 행렬을 다시 A라고 부를게요.
Back to -- okay. I'm looking at the columns of A.
A의 열들을 보는 겁니다.
Those are vectors in R^3. So the columns are in R^3. The columns are in R^3.
이 열들은 R³에 속해 있어요. R³ 안에 있는 벡터들이죠.
So I want those columns to be in my subspace.
그 열들이 내 부분공간 안에 있기를 원해요.
Now I can't just put two columns in my subspace
하지만 열 두 개만 넣고 "부분공간이다"라고 말할 수는 없어요.
and call it a subspace. What do I have to throw in -- if I'm going to put those two
그 열들을 포함하고 싶다면, 무엇까지 포함시켜야 할까요?
columns in, what else has got to be there to have a subspace? I must be able to add those things.
덧셈이 가능해야 해요. 두 열을 더한 것도 있어야 해요.
So the sum of those columns -- so these columns are in R^3, and I have to be able --
두 열의 합 — 예를 들어 (4,5,5) 같은 벡터도 포함돼야 해요.
I'm, you know, I want that to be in my subspace, I want that to be in my subspace, but therefore I have to be able to multiply them by anything.
그리고 첫 번째 열에 세 번째 열을 세 배 곱해서 더한 벡터도 있어야 해요.
Zero zero zero has got to be in my subspace. I have to be able to add them so that four five five
0 벡터도 반드시 있어야 하고요.
is in the subspace. I've got to be able to add one of these plus three of these. That'll give me some other vector.
즉, 모든 선형결합이 포함돼야 해요.
I have to be able to take all the linear combinations.
그래야 진짜 부분공간이 됩니다.
So these are columns in R^3 and all there linear combinations
다시 말해, 이 열들은 R³에 있는 벡터들이고, 그들의 모든 선형결합이 하나의 부분공간을 이룹니다.
form a subspace.
선형결합이란 건 뭐냐면, 하나에 어떤 수를 곱하고, 다른 것에도 어떤 수를 곱하고, 그걸 더하는 거예요.
The two operations of linear algebra, multiplying by numbers
선형대수에서의 두 가지 연산 — 스칼라 곱과 벡터 덧셈이죠.
and adding vectors. And, if I include all the results,
이 모든 연산 결과들을 포함시키면 그건 자동으로 부분공간이 돼요.
And we'll give it a name -- the column space.
그리고 우리는 거기에 이름을 붙일 거예요 — 바로 열공간(column space) 입니다.
Column space.
열공간.
And maybe I'll call it C of A. C for column space.
기호로는 C(A)라고 씁니다. C는 column의 첫 글자예요.
There's an idea there that --
여기에 중요한 개념이 숨어 있어요 —
Like, the central idea for today's lecture is --
오늘 강의의 중심 개념은 이거예요:
got a few vectors. Not satisfied with a few vectors, we want a space of vectors.
벡터 몇 개만으로는 만족하지 않아요. 우리는 벡터의 공간이 필요해요.
The vectors, they're in -- these vectors in -- are in R^3 , so our space of vectors will be vectors in R^3.
이 벡터들은 R³ 안에 있는 거니까, 우리가 만들 벡터 공간도 R³ 안에 있어요.
The key idea's -- we have to be able to take their combinations.
핵심은 — 이 벡터들로부터 선형결합을 만들 수 있어야 한다는 거예요.
So tell me, geometrically, if I drew all these things -- like if I drew one two four, that would be somewhere maybe
자, 기하적으로 생각해봅시다. 벡터 (1,2,4)를 그리면 아마 이쯤일 거고,
there. If I drew three three one, who knows, might be -- I don't know, I'll say there.
벡터 (3,3,1)은 — 어딘지는 모르겠지만 이쯤이라고 해봅시다.
There's column one, there's column two. What else -- what's in the whole column space?
그게 첫 번째 열, 두 번째 열이에요.
How do I draw the whole column space now? I take all combinations of those two vectors.
그럼 전체 열공간은 뭐죠?
Do I get -- well, I guess I actually listed the possibilities.
이 두 벡터의 모든 선형결합을 생각하는 겁니다.
Do I get the whole space? Do I get a plane?
전체 공간을 얻을까요? 아니면 평면일까요?
I get more than a line, that's for sure. And I certainly get more than the zero vector, but I do get the zero vector included.
직선보다는 많고, 0 벡터보다는 많지만, 0 벡터도 포함돼 있어요.
What do I get if I combine -- take all the combinations of two vectors in R^3 ?
두 벡터의 선형결합을 모두 취하면 R³ 전체가 되진 않겠죠.
So I've got all this stuff on --
그럼 무엇이 될까요?
that whole line gets filled out, that whole line gets filled out, but all in-between gets filled out -- between the two lines because I --
하나의 직선도 채워지고, 다른 직선도 채워지고, 그 사이의 모든 벡터들도 채워집니다.
I allowed to add something from one line, something from the other. You see what's coming?
왜냐하면 한쪽에서 나온 벡터, 다른 쪽에서 나온 벡터를 더할 수 있으니까요.
I'm getting a plane.
결국 평면이 나오는 거예요.
That's my -- and it's through the origin.
그리고 그건 원점을 지나는 평면입니다.
Those two vectors, namely one two four and three three one,
이 두 벡터, (1,2,4)와 (3,3,1)을 가지고
when I take all their combinations, I fill out a whole plane. Please think about that.
모든 선형결합을 만들면 하나의 평면을 채우게 돼요. 꼭 생각해 보세요.
That's the picture you have to see. You sure have to see it in R^3 , because we're going to do it
이 그림을 머릿속에 그릴 수 있어야 해요. R³에서는 그게 가능하죠. 왜냐하면
in R^10, and we may take a combination of five vectors in R^10, and what will we have?
곧 R¹⁰에서도 이걸 해야 하거든요. 예를 들어, R¹⁰에서 벡터 5개를 조합한다고 하면
God knows. It's some subspace. We'll have five vectors.
그 결과는 뭘까요? 신만 알겠죠. 어쨌든 부분공간 하나가 나옵니다.
They'll all have ten components. We take their combinations.
그 벡터들은 전부 성분이 10개고, 우리는 그 선형결합을 생각하는 거예요.
We don't have R^5 , because our vectors have ten components.
R⁵는 아니에요. 왜냐하면 벡터들의 성분 수가 10개니까요.
And we possibly have, like, some five dimensional flat thing
대신, 원점을 지나는 5차원의 평면(flat) 같은 게 나올 수도 있어요.
going through the origin for sure. Well, of course, if those five vectors were all on the line,
물론 그 5개 벡터가 모두 같은 직선 위에 있다면, 우리가 얻는 건 그 직선 하나뿐이에요.
then we would only get that line. So, you see, there are, like, other possibilities here. It depends what -- it depends on those five vectors.
이처럼 가능성은 다양해요. 결국은 벡터들이 어떤 형태이냐에 달렸어요.
Just like if our two columns had been on the same line, then the column space would have been only a line.
방금도 열 두 개가 같은 직선 위에 있었다면, 열공간도 직선이 됐겠죠.
Here it was a plane. Okay.
하지만 여기선 평면이 됐어요. 좋아요.
I'm going to stop at that point. That's the central idea of -- the great example of how
여기서 오늘은 마무리할게요. 이게 핵심 개념입니다 — 행렬로부터 부분공간을 만드는 훌륭한 예제예요.
to create a subspace from a matrix. Take its columns, take their combinations,
행렬의 열을 가져오고, 그 선형결합을 모두 취하면
all their linear combinations and you get the column space.
그게 바로 열공간입니다.
And that's the central sort of -- we're looking at linear algebra at a higher level.
그리고 이건 선형대수를 더 높은 관점에서 보는 출발점이죠.
When I look at A -- now, I want to look at Ax=b. That'll be the first thing in the next lecture.
다음 강의에서는 A와 Ax=b를 다시 살펴볼 거예요.
How do I understand Ax=b in this language --
이 새로운 언어 — 벡터공간과 열공간의 언어로 Ax=b를 어떻게 이해할 수 있을지 말이죠.
And what are other subspaces? So the column space is a big one, there are others to come.
그리고 다른 부분공간들도 있어요. 열공간이 가장 대표적인 것이고, 나머지는 이후에 다룰 거예요.
Okay, thanks.
좋습니다. 감사합니다.